so this is the middle length discourse
uh number
40 the shter discourse at
Asura and the Buddha goes and saying
recluses recluses because that is how
people perceive you and when you are
asked what are you you claim that you
are reuses since that since that is what you
reuses since that since that is what you
are designated and what you claim to be
you should train thus we will practice
the way proper to the recluse so that
our designations may be true and our
claims genuine and so that the services
of those who whose robes Els food
resting place and medicines we use shall
bring them great fruit and benefit and
so that our going forth shall not be
vain but fruitful and
fertile and how does a biku not practice
the way proper to the re to the
recluse for so long as a biku who is
Covetous has not abandoned covetousness
who has a mind of ill will ill will and
has not abandoned ill will who has a
mind of filled with defilements and has
not abandoned
defilements who has wrong View and has
not abandoned wrong view for so long he
does not practice the way proper to the
ReUse I say because of his failure to
abandon these stains for the recluse
these faults for the
recluse which are grounds for rebirth in
a state of deprivation and whose results
are to be experienced in an unhappy
destination he says I do not say that
the recluses status comes about in a rag
robe wearer through the mere wearing of
rag robes
knowing well basically any aesthetic
practice you don't become a aesthetic
th you don't become Reckless through
aestheticism through aism yeah but
standing on one leg and
so so it is if through the mere wearing
of uh rag
robes one who is a rag R wearer who was
covetousness Covetous abandoned
covetousness
then his friends and Companions and
Kinsmen and relatives would make him a
rag r as soon as he was born and have
him undertake the rag robe wearing
thus come my dear be a rag robe wearer
so that by mere wearing of a rag robe
when you when you are defiled you will
abandon defilement when you have wrong
view you abandon wrong
view it would be that easy exactly the
work would be done for you
through wearing the just wearing the r
robes yeah so
going so and how does a biku practice
the way proper to a reuse when any biku
who has a defilement abandons defilement
he has wrong View and he abandons wrong
view then he practices the way proper to
The Reckless he sees himself purified of
all these evil unome he sees himself
liberated from them when he sees this
gladness is born in him when he's glad
Rapture is born in him in one who
rapturous enjoys the body becomes see
that that that that very thing that very
thing you just read kind of on one on
one hand it's
uh it sounds
obvious self-explanatory but then on the other
self-explanatory but then on the other
hand nobody seems to do it as in like
even people who committed to the
practice they don't see
directly that these states are
abandoned and then the gladness result
it's all based on some sort of Faith
approximation of I'll do this then this
will happen I'll practice this then I
might have experience of that but a
direct knowledge recognition of this is
wholesome this is UNH wholesome un
wholesome is abandoned because of that
I'm glad and raptured and so on
uh that's completely
absent although it's an obvious passage
like you can read it as you just did and
okay yeah of course but not many people
would recognize that's that's all to it
in a way that's all the work that needs
to be done it's within that line you
just read not elsewhere not before or after
read not elsewhere not before or after
or in some different notes understanding
un wholesome and then abandoning it and
then knowing there are no wholesome
State present and that gives rise
automatically to gladness because you feel like you've
to gladness because you feel like you've
done the work the right
work and then the only reason natural
conclusion is the only reason why people
wouldn't be seeing that and would be
doing all sorts of other practices and
methods and techniques and Fates and
traditions and whatnot is because they
don't they don't understand what
wholesome is not un wholesome there's no
understanding of it first thing if you
ask someone do you know what ill will is
yeah I know yeah that's what I mean so
that that's the that's the whole point
is need toiz which
means his knowledge of ill will is not
the right knowledge his knowledge of
non-ill will is not the right knowledge
his knowledge of sensuality of
non-sensuality his knowledge of Right
View and wrong view are not the right
knowledges m in other words nobody
denies that somebody who started a
practice or been practicing for a long
time buta doesn't know
anything but if they're still not s
they themselves should not regard their
knowledge as uh as valid because because
of that they will keep making effort
further until they they they verify it
with their own like basically
understanding of freedom from
suffering so yeah exactly that's what
every person should be questioning
themselves oh wait a minute I'm reading
all these sutas about real will and here
I'm talking like I should do this I
should do that but do I even know what a
phenomenon of ill will is
what am I designating when I say ill
will what what am I referring to what is
it is it a state of mind what is it just
don't look for information to stand for
the answer just ask yourself what is it
in your very experience at the same time
that you are pointing at when you say
this ill
will what is it is it a pressure in your
chest is it the redness in your face but
then if you look closely you realize
Well it can't be that cuz those are the
results of the ill will so what is the
ill will so that's like people think that
will so that's like people think that
putuj can become
soana through kind of upgrading their
understanding you know getting the the
the more
accurate uh truth based on what you what
you kind of know about life get get a
greater insights into higher Universal
nature of things but that's completely
the wrong direction pujja can become
soana when he completely undoes
everything that makes him not when he
builds on top of it the new ideas and
new views and new experiences but when
he really UND does all of it that he
is with instruction from the sutas that
state then is where the Right View can
take place when the state of pojen has been
undone so for example if someone my mind
Focus ill
will what is ill
will so in order exactly so you can oh
am I am I am I engaging in your will now
you can say yes or no but then you go
further okay
but do understand what your will is what
am I asking myself
here so it's a lack of that kind of
right reflection on the basic nature of
designation in terms that you already
use thatan already uses that's why he
keeps maintaining his wrong views not
because he hasn't make made enough
effort invested in some technique or or
practice of restraint he probably made
too much but none of that can make any
much but none of that can make any
fundamental
difference because he hasn't
uprooted the wrong views where they
should have been
uprooted he just took aspects of those
views for granted and then started his
practice as a as a building further on
top of it which means me no matter how
many stories you built you built it on
completely improper foundation so you
can't go as as sufficiently sufficiently
high because foundations can't support
it so instead of trying to find out the
answers you really need to understand
what do you what are you even
asking what are you referring to when
you ask these questions and ill will was
just one example just take any of the
Aggregates ask yourself about your own
feelings when you say oh I'm feeling like this
when you say oh I'm feeling like this
today now don't worry about the content
of it just think about as the the
designation word feeling that you used
in whatever language you would have used
it and ask yourself okay but what am I
what am I referring to what am I
pointing at what am I designating with
this designation of my language in this
designation of my language in this
experience so what is that feeling that
I just said it's such and such
can I describe it can I understand it
can I see its
nature oh no the feelings imp yeah
that's all great that's all what you
heard that's all your information your
third person view your theory which is
necessary to have but if you stay on the
level of it it can never really result
in an Insight that
matters you want to see for you at the
time of saying my feeling is such and
such what do you refer to when you say
that feeling
what is it how far you can designate it
how far you can discern it without then
everything else you think about a
feeling is put it aside first start
seeing what is being experienced as a
feeling when you say
feeling that's when the suits when
sometimes when the monks would try to
understand something they would say it
like like oh feeling feeling what is
feeling or first J first J what is first
J say that loud that's how you bring it
to your mind once twice three times and
then okay so now this enduring
experience of having just said this out
loud within this enduring experience I
can hopefully start Discerning the
direction where that feeling actually is
what am I referring to and you realize
that any of the five or all of the five
agregates are modeled in your own
understanding in regard to your own five
agregates so people go through their
life using words like matter feeling my
perception or my Consciousness my
intentions but the understanding of that
is completely
it's just a concoction of various
Concepts and ideas never question often
self-contradictory and on top of it then
you try to practice the Dharma as in
keep adding
more but the right practice of Dharma is
undoing the ignorance not adding the
right knowledge on top of the ignorance
that's not a
knowledge so you undo by reverting back
to questioning the basic nature of it
not denying it not affirming it just
putting it in question so that you can
see what is there enduring that you just
refer to as
feeling what is there no there's no
feeling there's nothing there's nothing
nothing's permanent that's another third
person view assumption in regard to own
experience that you just jump into out
of your views and ideas put all that
aside ask yourself feeling feeling what
is my feeling right here right now oh
I'm feeling Pleasant okay so in that
designation feeling Pleasant what is the
feeling aspect of that
Pleasant what do you refer to because if
there was nothing to refer to you
wouldn't use that word as a
designation it would be just a hollow
sound just a pointless sound and we
don't use pointless sounds like that so
even when there's something not
understood in the case ofj the nature
his aggregate completely
muddled uh he still refers to something
and that's the starting point what is
that something you are referring to when
you say my
perception if I just go back to that's
ill will like if I say if I question is
my mind defined what do I mean by
defined well exactly in order to
question yourself rightly see the would
have said that the monk will do that
which means he already has undone all
these wrong views about what ill will is
what defilement is he already knows
these things so then that kind of
questioning can be right and
productive but yes you can start is my
mind defiled okay so what is that
defilement what do I mean by defilement
I know what defilement means in theory
in the dictionary definition in the
polych society dictionary I know what
defilement is but what is it for me when
I say defilement what am I referring to
and then look at what you're referring
to and see if it matches what you think
Defan is and that's how you start to undo the
is and that's how you start to undo the
layers of of this model thinking in
regard to the basic phenomena of your
experience the nature of phenomen of
your experience so
yeah in terms of like e will again so go
to it's like resistance in regard to
something to a feeling true but then you
need to know what feeling is
sure so if you look what ill will is
well that's how you also know it you
don't I need to know this before I can
do this no you start doing it that's how
you realize how much you don't know by
knowing how much you don't know you know
exactly how much you need to learn but
if you don't start a questioning you
won't even know how much you you don't
know and that's the worst type of
ignorance so yeah ill will what am I
referring to as ill will how would I
describe it well first and obvious it's
it well first and obvious it's
unpleasant okay so ill will is
unpleasant but it's a resistance towards
something yeah exactly so you can take
further now you can go into like
psychologizing mode but again that's you
assuming the third person view in regard
to your own experience of ill will you
don't want to do that what you want to
do is repeating the question if your
mind won't stay on it if he hasn't been
learn if it hasn't been taught how to
think properly keep repeating it and
keep dwelling on the topic without
giving into self kind of in fabricated
third person explanations based on the
theory you
read nor do you mystify oh will is
inexplicable well you just explain it by
calling it inexplicable that is that is
clearly its property then which means
it's not trly liable which means your
own designation contradicted itself so
those are the criteria don't contradict
yourself don't assume the third person
view so how else would you then describe
the ill will there not onean
thing well that's it see not wanting not
wanting and we said what's the basic
characteristic of it's unpleasant so
which one is it that you don't want the
unpleasantness of your will or the will
the unpleasantness exactly yeah so you
realize if say theoretically ill will
would not be unpleasant and that's how
when people say they have anger problem
they have anger problem when they start
basically like um bitterly
indulging getting the bitter pleasure
out of the anger yeah and they're always
angry about
something so in order for them to undo
that ill will they first need to stop
enjoying it and see for what it is which
is
unpleasant yeah it's because it's
there's unpleasant yeah that you well
you wanted you have to deal with it
because it's unpleasant you want to get
rid of it you either get rid of fin
enjoying it or you get rid of it by
dismissing engaging in ill will is a
form of
pleasure it's it's a form of trying to
escape the pain yeah
yeah so first and foremost then if you
want to overcome the will you have to
stop acting habitually and the Habit in
this case as we just clarify is trying
to avoid unpleasant unpleasant feeling
displeasure so that's all it takes if
you're able to hold the unpleasant
feeling for as long as it endures you
won't give into it will thus you have no
anger problem anger problem is when you can't
problem anger problem is when you can't
restrain
yourself and again all of this now that
we just described came from basic
questioning what is your will in my
experience not what is your will for me
as in it can mean something else for
somebody else no what are the universal
characteristics of the phenomenon of
real will it's unpleasant thus there is
will it's unpleasant thus there is
resistance in regard to that
displeasure because of that you then
give in to the proposed actions of your
real will they not just distract you
from this pleasure but off a certain
like amount of pleasurable just
Justified pleasure through like oh well
justice has been served you know he done
me he done me harm I I retaliated now I
feel good or or things like that or just
just generally letting it out there
affecting others will will distract you
from your own pain and provide you with
pleasure by through seeing their own
suffering it's when people act out of
ill will then to abandon you he abandons
you will so what motivates you will then
it's running away from your own
displeasure you want to uh UNM motivate
the act of ill will stop running away
from your own displeasure there is no
Outlet will then completely cut at its
root and and for like Envy meant to sh
Envy one who EnV again same what is Envy
in it's in fundamental characteristic is
it Pleasant or unpleasant yeah it's
unpleasant it's unpleasant exactly
exactly so if you take that feeling for
granted you will take your attitude
towards that feeling for granted feeling
of displeasures taken for granted me not
wanting this pleasure is taken for
granted then the out output of that
attitude it's going to be envy Envy ill
will centrality for that matter any of
it wishes sorry evil evil wishes yeah
yeah yeah yeah deceitfulness everything
UNH wholesome will come simply CU you
are unaware and muddled in regard to the
nature of the present enduring feeling
in your own
experience not yesterday not tomorrow
not before or after right here right now
while you are being engaging or
restraining from engaging you know those
those acts so you if you approve the attitude
acts so you if you approve the attitude
in regard to the presently Oris feeling
in your experience you approv the whole
kind of laid out paved out ways of the
proliferation of un wholesome but if you
go around trying to chase every
individual un wholesome and trim it back
yeah good luck with that that's why the
Buddha said you you it's like a palm
stump killed at its
root you don't go around trimming the
bre branches they've been proliferated
this way or that way you realize well
that's a waste of effort and certainly
not going to solve the problem you kill
its roots and then whatever it's been
proliferated you don't care about it no
amount of Pathways of ill will will make
a difference when there is no ill will
to go along those
Pathways that's why it's just like a
palm stump dried up cut up destroyed at
its roote it won't grow
again and that's it again there was that
was a passage that
probably many many people in the past
and in the future would just read over
and yeah of course you abandon un
wholesome you get joy and stuff the
whole teaching is in it so if you don't
know what un wholesome is you won't know
what wholesome is so how can you then do
that question that the Buddha talks
about well I'll tell you how people
might think oh I don't
care but for example it's in this it's
in this okay well if the sud says it
then it's fine well well this to what I
just read there the abandoning of un
wholesome sure he he does this he
abandons wrong view sure so he gets
Right View and he's happy because he's
purified of evil and wholesome States
and his mind becomes composed so
some and as a
result of that composure and that
abandonment of evil and wholesome States
it goes into he abides pervading one
quarter with a mind imbued with
kindness with a
mind um so what is without hostility and
without ill
will but somehow this whole suit has
been turned upside down in a way first
one assumes I will abide pervading one
quarter with a mind with love kindness
and then I will eventually abandon e
I will eventually gain some I will
eventually be purified of all evil and
wholesome States yeah but if you read
the Su you already need to understand first
Su you already need to understand first
yeah fully what wholesome and UNH
wholesome is you need to abandon the
wrong view fully you need to become Sana
then be glad because you're free from
UNH wholesome and then you pervade your
experience with that gladness which is
drama vas yeah it's autom you just
recognize yeah it's a result of right
understanding it's not not a method or
some visualization or whatever wishful
thinking they will then miraculously C
cure you from your ill will and
everything else it's very easy to assume
that okay now if I just the opposite of
ill will is no because people yes
because people are used to doing things
that's what ignorant mind does just I'm
doing this I'm doing that I'm choosing
this I'm choosing that so if you start
telling them okay but now you need to
understand the nature of your action
and they would say okay so what do I do
because that is the threshold of of
put's mind that he can't think below
that what can be done so I must do
something so they might see the point
they might get the hints and see the
signs of ah understanding the nature of
action frees you from action yeah that's
insightful but they still going to have
trouble finding the direction to go to
see that without doing
it so what do I do and then we when they
come in C instruction what you do you
understand UNH wholesome you understand
wholesome you abandon the wrong view do
that okay but what do I do in order to
do that yeah as in tell me how to
move and you could see it's only natural
then to pervert your order and assume ah
okay so I will sit in my room and I will
and I will send positive thoughts to my
enemies and I will think well about
everyone and I will be kind and I will
do this and I will do this and I will do
this and through that magical doing I'm
going to have a magical result of being
free from action so through doing action
I'm going to free myself from doing
action and they remain oblivious to that
blatant contradiction but it's not about what
contradiction but it's not about what
you do it's whether you understand the
phenomenon of doing so in this case ill
will ill will you know what you should
not do don't engage with your will at
its face value as in be strength and
develop virtue beforehand so you can do
that type of negative action abstain
from UNH wholesome action you do that
okay so what do I do next then well next
ask yourself the questions whether you
even understand things in your
experience presently there because when
you say oh my ill will is sort of I'm
I'm currently restraining my acts of ill
will say somebody says that and if you
were to ask them okay so what is that
ill will that you designate to
it if they give any answer except the
answer that pertains to the present
situation it's going to be the wrong
answer because they that ill will is
there when they made that designation so
if they have to resort to Theory or
explanation means they don't see it they
just set serve another view that stands
in place of it another assumption of
what your will is but the point is as
long as you serve assumptions you serve
Opana basically you serve your own
holding through taking things at face
value so if somebody says oh currently
I'm experiencing my mind is in a state
of ill will on account of such and such
reasons put reasons
aside allow the presently Arison ill
will to endure and then investigate that
not through Theory not through third
person view not through psychologizing
but what are the characteristics of this
experience as a whole affected by ill
will just what we done 10 minutes ago
well the first and
obvious it's unpleasant okay so the Char
istic of ill will is unpleasant could I
regard that to be a universal
characteristic of ill will as in is
there sometimes ill will that I don't
feel pressured or sort of affected by no
there isn't so you could safely say
you're not ultimately sure but you don't
need to be because at least you're
thinking on the basic of presently
enduring things not on the basis of
theory Scholastic investigation mystical
whatever psychologizing no presently
what you're experiencing that's what
you're trying to clarify to yourself
just through what it's there looking at
the signs and tokens of those
things so when you're okay so ill will
is always pressuring me whenever I can
remember in the F in the past whatever I
can think like I'm experience it's going
to be if if it's still will this is the
nature is going to be shared it's
unpleasant pressure in me so then you so
my acts on account of your will things I
used to do things that I'm restraining
now and things that I hope I won't do in
the future
are they rooted in ill will in itself as
in if the act of Aris ill will contains
the implication of these actions or is
just my attitude towards that pressure
of unpleasantness of ill will and ah
it's my attitude okay so that's why the
Trin needs to come first again an
obvious thing that very few people would
actually see on the basis of presently
enduring things I mean many people keep
the precepts
perfectly and still remain penous
completely no
understanding and that's why because
they haven't understood it any of it on
the presently enduring
basis but if you st you realize within
two sentences that's why you must it's
not negotiable you must restrain first
because it doesn't come from the Arisen
experience of will will or cality for
the matter it's my doing on account of
it and if if I keep doing that at its
face value how can I free myself like
basically if I pressure you and you
cannot help by responding I will always
know my pressure
works so you want to free yourself from
my pressure over you yet you can't help
responding so that's a contradiction in
terms even if you say well I Want to Be
Free the fact that you keep responding
to my pressure I know you're not free
mhm so first you have to stop responding
to the pressure of real will or the
pressure of sensuality hence virtue is
not negotiable virtue comes
first then you then there's already a
basis of clarity there okay so that's
why I must and when there's Clarity in
regard to restraint means there is
understanding in regard to the nature of
restraint which means you're doing it
less blindly now and you're actually
seeing how it pertains to the practice
okay so it's not direct and you also
understand that my restraint does not
miraculously result in Freedom from ill
will but now you know exactly why is it
necessary oh so I have to stop giving
into the pressure in order to free
myself from the pressure and you again
you don't see it as a theory you see it
on a presently and during basis of that
ill will and then you can carry on with that
will and then you can carry on with that
questioning okay so now that I am
restrained that I have clarified that
with relative certainty that Universal
characteristic of will will it's
unpleasant and pressuring
me what go a step further and then as we
as we done so so what is it then that
that's unpleasant in
it is there a particular content or just
do you have a say over which aspect is
going to bother you of that ill will do
you ever say which part will be
unpleasant you you don't it just has a
reason as a package so it's speak ill
will unpleasant pressure on account of
this or this or this or that but the
point is ill will in its nature presses
so it's being felt
unpleasantly so the experience of ill
will means experience of feeling
displeasure so really now you're not concerned with
so really now you're not concerned with
ill will anymore you're concerned with
the gratuitous attitude of craving for
the absence of the disagreeable
feeling and then you carry on the same
questioning as we done in other talks
okay so feeling feeling then what is the
feeling when I refer to it again not
before after yesterday tomorrow new
Theory new suit right here right now on
the basis of your will that I've been
self- investigating let me ask myself if
question now that I've discerned that is
a feeling behind it that's where the
problem is rooted so the presently
enduring disagreeable feeling of a
particularly manifested ill will so that
unpleasant feeling what is its
nature how would you describe it in most
general terms oh the Buddha no doesn't matter
terms oh the Buddha no doesn't matter
what the Buddha said or who said what
for you right now that feeling of
disagreeable that keeps enduring for
while we're talking all of this
how would you describe it in your own
terms don't worry about being right or
wrong and as pretty much everybody I
would ever asked this question said oh
well it's just there that will be the
common threat CU yeah it's just there if
something is just there you have no idea
why or how for whether it's just there
you subjected to it so if something
that's just there that you just
subjected to it that you can only only
sort of act secondarily so to speak in
response to but you can't prevent from
arising why you regarding that thing is
yours why are you taking your attitude
of
response at face
value because your attitude of response
implies that you can do something about
that thing just being there oppressing
you but when you look at it close you
realize I have even no idea how this
thing came to be how long it will be let
alone how to like make it go away when I
want to that's what the Buddha would say
oh well if the pleasant is feeling is
yours how about an unpleasant feeling or
or neutral feeling like feeling is mine
and he say well which
one cuz if feeling were truly yours you
would have only one feeling that you
want you would never experience feelings
that you don't want but because more
often than not you experience feelings
that you don't want you realize that
when you want feelings you actually
realize oh actually even that is not in
my
control and that's the nature of
sensuality it's all rooted in the same
response towards a risen feeling craving
response of craving and response where I
use the word response it's not a process
it's not a response in time it's a
simultaneously present attitude to the
simultaneously present phenomenon of
that particular
feeling sure it shouldn't be there but
for it is there that is his starting
point so whether it's ill will whether
it's any Envy whether you bring it down
and it's going to come down to how it's
being felt that experience as a whole
and it's going to come down to whether
you're trying to indulge the UN
wholesome get rid of it or distract
yourself from it greed lost a verion
delusion if you remove lost a verion
delusion you've removed the entire
universe of un wholesome possibilities
of un wholesome cannot manifest that
so so one sees it I can't I can't see
any craving yeah in got feel yeah
because you don't see the feeling no
well so if you say I can't see any
craving the answer basically give you
only two answers you're either an arant
or your putan who doesn't even see the
nature of the presently enduring feeling
right so there's a there is no third
option there's other resistance towards
a feeling or a welcoming and delighting
in that feeling or covering up or kind
of so what is in common to resisting the
feeling welcoming the feeling covering
up the feeling what's in common to these
three things except feeling okay except
uh
craving okay so craving fine but craving
for many people they think they
understood craving they understood World
craving so how would you then describe
that craving that's in common to these
three attitudes towards the feeling what
would be characteristics of of the
craving uh an attitude of an attitude of
pressure see like that's normal and
people would stop and think that but
well go back to the present inuring
feeling how am I feeling right now I'm
feeling neutral well the Buddha said in
regard to neutral feeling there there is
a tendency towards
ignorance towards distraction towards
Oblivion and the tendency is where the
craving is so what would be then in your own
is so what would be then in your own
words the characteristic of that
tendency of the kind of present enduring
feeling even if you're not necessarily
doing the distraction you can recognize
the tendency to do so in regard to
neither unpleasant or Pleasant feeling
wanting just wanting to wanting but
wanting is already the result of it yeah
but so when you want
something different from what it is now
enduring how would you describe that who
resisted who resists
what me resisting you resisting the the
Arisen
feeling and then what you do what do you
want to do
I want it to change you want to replace
it exactly exactly but if you go back to
see what you're resisting as we just
done here you realize he has risen on
its own enduring yet you want to
override it and you realize how futile that
it and you realize how futile that
is because the only way you can override
something is if you have a say but if
something is just there on its own
oppressing you or Reason on its own
enduring on its own you are subjected to
it it's not subjected to
you why are you entertaining Notions of
overriding it when you can't even
conceive where or how that would be
possible so then you realize you can
entertain Notions of overriding it by
not understanding what it is that you
resist and try to override hence
ignorance results in that craving or
rather ignorance fuels the
craving so if you stop ignoring
the nature of that which is there that
you're trying to resist can you then
still engage in the acts of
craving well and there's not I don't
think there would be
a uh you wouldn't have to try to un
engage exactly cuz if you don't ignore
it there is no room for craving or non-
craving for like well it's absence of
craving basically there is no room for
wanting or not wanting in that sense
because both can be a craving I want
this I don't want this either way you
crave but as we just clarified again on
the basis of the present enduring
feeling if you stop ignoring the obvious
Universal nature of that enduring
phenomenon that you're
feeling you will then stop entertaining
the Notions of craving yeah no matter
what you feel no matter what you feel
because you understood the nature of
feeling in general cuz you stopped
ignoring the right nature natural
feeling so that's when people are
mindfulness and then like touching
moving moving looking looking it's not
mindfulness of everything and nothing at
the same time it's mindfulness of
feelings thoughts or intentions either
way they're going to boil down to
feeling and craving towards
feelings so mindfulness of the present
enduring feeling in the background of
your experience what is the present mood
what is the basis of it is it Pleasant
unpleasant neutral that's your starting
point that's what you don't lose the
sight of if you don't lose the sight of
it you cannot ignore its nature and the
nature of these things that have Arisen
for you the Buddha said
himself not it's a
and well then your experience will be
anata if you see that nature because if
you see the
nature but basically if you like all of
this attitude of resisting craving they
all come from the view of I am in charge
I am in
control because of that I will replace
this because of that I will make this St
longer but you could see like even that
I am in control and I will do all of
this is because of your ignorance of
what you're trying to replace ignorance
of the nature of it which if you press
yourself far enough in the questioning
the answer is going to be oh well it's
just there I don't know how
why how long for what reason the feeling
is just there and it's felt like this it
oppresses me I don't oppress it
I'm subjected to it and you cannot even
conceive even people who are full
on believing the self self-centered
whatever
megalomaniac even they could not ignore
that the fact that all of your sense of
self and your responses are secondary to
the fact that thing has arisen first on
its own mhm and you are subjected to it
and that's what
need exactly exactly so recognizing the
characteristics of these things that
determine you that's why the Buddha said
um
saara because the self view sense of
self is on the level of
dharm not on the level well it's related
to the level of Sara but it's not there
so it's not like everything is
impermanent everything is suffering
everything is not self no that's a third
person view about everything no you want
to see that presently Arisen things for
me that determine
me are Arisen on its own and they're
oppressing me and those things I've been
talking about that's exactly what anicha
and Dua is it's not like like pleasure
is oppressing you daoka is not like pain
and pain everywhere just
pain daoka is being oppressed daa is
being uneasy because you are not in
control fundamentally things are thrust on you
fundamentally things are thrust on you
you just subjected to this which is just
there so the questioning we've been
doing again the entire Dharma is
contained in it all of it anich Dua
whatever so you could see if you discern
the peripheral feeling the mood that you
are in whatever you're doing
particularly this or that we're not
talking the background of your mood what
is what is the fundamental how would you
label it positive negative maybe neutral
well it's it's positive I feel okay I
feel light and easy whatever else means
it's Pleasant so that is universal nature so
Pleasant so that is universal nature so
that pleasure endures can endure for
days sometimes even in putous minds or
something bothersome this disagreable
feeling can fundamentally endure for
days on a particular level you can have
this Pleasant feeling and this pleasant
but there particular where you looking
at the most General nature of what's
overall being felt
and that's what the craving is so if you
stop ignoring what's overall being felt
and in order to stop ignoring that you
have to stop giving into the particular
Pursuits of sensuality to particular
denials of your will and to particular
distractions of your
mindfulness then you will be aware of
your mood you will be aware of the
enduring feeling on that fundamental
basis the more you aware of the
right the more you're aware of the
feeling on that right level the less you
will be able to entertain things that
directly arise on account of unawareness
of that
feeling that's basic composure of
mindfulness if you want to do a proper
rep person then B on the basis of that
composure you ask this questions we just
done what would be the universal
characteristic how would I describe this
in end during feeling they clearly now
endures for two or 3 days I'm not saying
it it just happens to be pleasant so I
don't feel threatened by it but you
don't feel threatened by the particular
pleasure of that feeling so you want to
look Beyond that's what I mean what's
Universal what is you can ask yourself
what is in common to this fundamentally
Pleasant mood that I have what's in
common to this and to unpleasant mood
that I had or will have in the future or
the neutral mood so you stop being
concerned with Pleasant unpleasant
neutral you start looking at the nature
of that feeling that is Pleasant
unpleasant and then again you don't need
to oh it's an it's an no if you say that
then ask yourself what is a for me what
am I designating by an you want to
discern the characteristics of that
feeling and those characteristics will
be anich Anda because the Buddha himself
said he didn't invent D he didn't he
created this he rediscovered it he was
always there that's why freedom from
ignorance is
possible because if you look at these
things genuinely correctly
sufficiently that is their nature it's
just there means I'm not its creator
means it's just there now but when it
isn't it won't be means it's permanent
impermanent means it cannot be
owned because it's just there can I
bring it into me and assimilate its old
domain make it mine you can't you can
get closer to it you can have this
attitude or that attitude more attitude
less attitude for the duration of any of
that that thing will always be there on
its own
enduring what is the what is the what is
what is another
characteristic of that what is the
universal characteristic of pleasant
feeling unpleasant feeling or neutral
feeling not in theory but on the basis
of pleasant feeling that you're
currently feeling Pleasant mood
it's just there we said that
M you have no idea you can't even
conceive where how the feeling you can
explain using modern science and whatnot
but all of that is secondary to the fact
that this thing is just there you can't
go through it and see what's behind the
feeling that is your bottom yeah I have
no choice in it you have no choice in
the matter which means who is who is
basically subordinate to who
are your feelings subordinate to you or
actually your own choice and intention
volition is subordinate to the presently
arason feeling that's just there so it
oppresses you it controls you and that's
unpleasant so we already described anich
and Dua on account of the
characteristics that anybody who starts
this questioning can start seeing on
account of presently enduring feeling
but again I insist present enduring
feeling must be on the level of the most
General background of the mood that you
are in not on account of oh I'm looking
this I'm feeling light in my body stuff
all of that is secondary to a sense of
self but mood never is like you can you
can you can like tell yourself you're
Master controller of experience but
moods fundamentally good bad or neutral
is something that always comes
underneath you so that's why if you go
that far to discern the nature of the
feeling or you have to go that far to
discern the nature of the feeling cuz
that's the way that you cannot re
converted back so to speak to being mine
any lesser feeling than that can be
appropriated easily because your sense
of self remains kind of impartial to
it but that's not really the feeling
you're looking
for the fundamentally is it positive
negative or neutral that you have no say
in and you will arrive at that through
ill will questioning the ill will
questioning anything un wholesome
questioning centrality
centrality
all we'll arrive at the same
point seeing Saras as anicha as
oppressing youa and then automatically
you will not be able to entertain the
notion that you are Master controller of
your whole experience when you realize
you are the you are the one subjected to
it so then that experience of I'm the
master controller
he seeing Oh this is not my this is not
the master in
controller so that experience becomes
the experience of
AATA that wrong view is
aband exactly yeah yeah you think oh I
contr so that's where anicha is it's not
like what yourself sees it's what
undermines your sense of self which is
the fire Aggregates that's why somebody
who has discerned this as would with say
would just stay mindful of manifestation
of the Aggregates coming and going
arising and passing and whatever
translation is because that's that's where the
is because that's that's where the
characteristics are through staying
mindful of it you cannot ignore them
through not ignoring them you cannot
proliferate craving through not
proliferating craving you cannot suffer
anymore it's the same with the
intentions sure you find there is an
intention there towards same with any AG
basically but obviously the feeling is
where things converge so to speak you
intend yeah yeah and because you feel
like if people were not starting with
wrong views then in theory they could
pick up any Aggregate and question it
rightly but everybody starts with wrong
views and the convergence of the wrong
views is on craving and that's where the
feeling is so unless you start undoing
it from that basis and you say start
thinking about intentions of the nature
of Viana and whatnot you're not going to
be thinking on the present of presently
enduring phenomena but you can theoretically sure
phenomena but you can theoretically sure
you can say Consciousness Consciousness
when I say Consciousness in English or
in P or whatever language what am I
referring to in this experience right
here right now while I'm saying that
question what am I referring to what is
it tell me the characteristics of it but
they will be much harder much more
subtle my mind you Consciousness is the
most refined of all
as it would have said himself
but if one does that on the basis of the
presently enduring mood and feeling then
it becomes actually fully
intelligible then you know oh this is
what needs to be done most people most
people's relation with Buddhist practice
is magical
almost I believe that through being
virtuous I believe that through being
good I believe that through doing this
method and technique I believe through
the in sutas I'm going to have the
experience of
Enlightenment it's like I believe in
rebirth yeah I believe in everything B I
believe that me doing this to the left
is going to result in these things to
the right there's no connection between
the two that I can see or that I don't
have to fabricate for
myself but definition of the one who is
free from wrong view is he knows
wholesome as
wholesome and UNH wholesome as un
wholesome so he knows why good is good
and bad is bad he's not just believing
in
it and that's why he's free from Silas
virtue and
Duty oh it's my duty you know to sit and
watch in my nostrils because how else
can I become enlightened yeah but why is
that your duty ask yourself
that not like through fabricating
answers based on you know the
commentarial text you read and just
providing back information no presently
Arison cause has been presently
understood and that's the freedom from
suffering that's what it would have
said so do you understand presently
orent things and does that understanding
presently simultaneously free you from
that but if you never start questioning
it on that level how do you expect to
find it
out that's what said Del with a knife
like keep digging as in keep digging
back or in undoing the layers of your
views and what you think phenomena are
and feelings are and intentions are not
just all keep fabricating further and
you'll arrive at the right goal through
your state of pjan I know the only way
to arrive it go is to undo dismantle
stop feeding stop providing nutrients
for your state of
pja and that's usually
completely the opposite direction sorry
that's always the completely opposite
direction from where people usually tend
to
go in their
practice so when somebody approaches the
Su oh yeah yeah this this this this
makes sense makes sense instead of
building further you have to look back
now okay so I think think I understood
the suta and my ass as a result of it
suta and my ass as a result of it
because truly understanding a sutta will
mean at least the Right View no why is
that is the is it suta's fault is it
translation's fault well maybe to some
extent the translation's fault not the
sud's fault but really it's your
preconceived notions of the terms that
you reading in the
sutta those Notions are wrong because of
that your usage of the meanings in the
suta is
wrong so then you start undoing your
Notions of the wrong terms with the help
of the sutas that's how you get to read
them rightly